in this Baldur's Gate 3 wizard class
guide I'm going to be covering the
wizard class including all eight
subclasses and providing you some useful
information I'll be doing more build
guides for Baldur's Gate 3 and wizards
but for now let's just look at how
Wizards function and their basics
Wizards in bg3s serve several functions
within their group they not only have
offensive spells like Cloud kill but
many are utility oriented as well like
the knock spell which allows them to
open lock doors or chests or the
enlarged reduced spell which allows them
to change the size of a creature they
differ from sorcers in several ways
namely that they learn nearly twice as
many spells from leveling up they can
learn spells from Scrolls they cannot
manipulate their spells with metamagic
they must prepare their spells in
advance before casting them and they use
intelligence to cast their spells
compared to the sorcerer's charisma
When comparing Wizard and sorcerer many
players lean towards sorcerer because of
Quicken spell which allows them to cast
two spells in one turn but what Wizards
lack in one turn Firepower they make up
in versatility
Sorcerers may not know the spell needed
for every occasion but Wizards typically
will especially if they learn from
Scrolls
wizard subclasses are made up mostly of
subclass features that reward the player
for casting a certain type of spell such
as evocation spells if you chose
evocation and also by reducing the cost
to learn spells of that type from
Scrolls players choose one of them
typically based on the type of spells
they like to cast most
Wizards have no armor proficiencies and
almost no weapon proficiencies making
them terrible in martial combat if they
don't multi-class and they don't have
Proficiency in Constitution saving
throws like Sorcerers making them
generally worse at maintaining
concentration
in this section we'll take a look at how
to set up your wizard during character
creation for best results we'll begin
with abilities first since this is
arguably the most important part aside
from choosing your subclass
your primary abilities as a wizard are
intelligence and Constitution
intelligence determines how difficult it
is for enemies to save against your
spells and prove spell attack rules
improves intelligent skill checks and
intelligence saving throws as well as
increases the amount of prepared spells
a wizard can have Constitution is there
to help keep you alive via HP and also
to help you maintain concentration on
spells like cloud of daggers hypnotic
pattern or whole person should they get
hit while concentrating on them
for this reason I strongly recommend
that you invest 16 into intelligence and
16 in a constitution during character
creation 14 decks 30 is also not bad to
improve your initiative which helps you
take your turn sooner in combat as well
as provide some Armor class
note I've changed this from the
recommendations as it's more optimized
for your character during the early
goings of the game
when it comes to races githyanki
provides the wizard with light and
medium armor proficiency they wouldn't
otherwise get as well as astral
knowledge allowing them to gain
Proficiency in one ability skill each
long rest they will also gain Misty Step
at level 5 which can help with wizard
positioning
half elf is good for light armor and
shield proficiency as well as Fey
ancestry and they also gain dark vision
which can help land your attacks in Dark
Places
human is also good for similar reasons
but they don't gain Fey ancestry or dark
vision but they will gain an extra skill
proficiency instead
elf is not bad for Fey ancestry and
perception proficiency they also gain
dark vision which can help land their
attacks in Dark Places and High Elves
gain an extra cantrip from the Wizard's
spell list
chill dwarf can also work for light and
medium armor proficiencies along with
dark vision and Dwarven resilience
for skills you'll want to focus on
intelligence-based ones unless you chose
githyanki and then you can use astral
knowledge to select intelligence Sage is
a great choice for Arcana in history and
then you can select investigation and
religion
next let's move on to wizard character
progression at level 1 Wizards gain
Arcane recovery which allows them to
replenish a level 1 spell slot outside
of combat once prolonged rest
Wizards will gain another charge of
Arcane recovery at every odd wizard
level allowing them to replenish more
and higher level spells Wizards will
also gain access to three cantrips and 6
level 1 Spells at this level along with
two level 1 spell slots
remember that Wizards need to prepare
these spells in order to cast them and
just because they know six spells
doesn't mean they can prepare them all
at this level
at level 2 Wizards will choose a
subclass and gain a subclass feature
from that subclass and we'll go into
this in more detail in the subclasses
section at level 3 wizards gain access
to level 2 spells and gain level 2 spell
slots and can upcast level 1 spells with
these slots if they can be many spells
in bg3 can be upcast for additional
damage or increased targets pay
attention to which spells they are so
you don't waste higher level spell slots
on ones that can't be at level 4 wizards
will gain their first feat ability
Improvement is a good choice to further
increase their intelligence modifier
which improves their spell DC spell
attack roles intelligent skill checks
and saves as well as allows them to
prepare one more spell resilient
Constitution is also not a bad choice
here if you find yourself casting a lot
of spells that require concentration as
this will allow you to add your
proficiency bonus to your concentration
saving throws when you get hit in combat
at level 5 Wizards gain access to level
3 spells and gain level 3 spell slots
and can upcast level 1 and 2 spells with
these slots if they can be at Level 6
wizards once again gain a subclass
feature that depends on the subclass
chosen we'll cover this in the
subclasses section
at level 7 Wizards gain access to level
4 spells and game level 4 spell slots
and can upcast level 1 2 and 3 spells
with these slots if they can be at level
8 Wizards gain their second feat ability
Improvement is still a good choice here
though you can choose resilient
Constitution if you haven't yet alert is
also not a terrible idea allowing you to
go sooner in combat so you can fling
spells before enemies can react
Elemental Adept is also an option if you
find yourself gravitating towards one
type of Elemental damage
at level 9 Wizards gain access to level
5 spells and gain level 5 spell slots
and can upcast level one two three and
four spells with these slots if they can
be
at level 10 Wizards gain their final
subclass feature and again we'll cover
this in the subclasses section
at level 11 Wizards gain access to level
6 spells and gain one level 6 spell slot
and can upcast level one two three four
and five spells with this slot if they
can be this is the highest level of
spells Wizards can learn in pg3
at level 12 Wizards gain their final
feat ability Improvement is still a good
choice here if you're not yet at 20
intelligence or you can choose from any
of the other ones I suggested before
moving on to equipment the equipment
Wizards use will vary greatly depending
on what race you selected they generally
wear no armor but since they can cast
spells in any armor they have
Proficiency in if you have lighter
medium from a race you should definitely
use that if you can the same goes for
Shields so if they have Shield
proficiency from human or half elf they
should definitely use one to beef up
their Armor class
when it comes to weapons it's not super
important because Wizards will likely
cast cantrips when they don't want to
use spell slots not attack with weapons
however look for something that gives
you a spell you can use or perhaps some
passive bonus to spell casting
next we'll move on to subclasses
choosing a wizard subclass in bg3 really
comes down to what spells you think
you'll use the most like offensive
spells like Fireball or lightning bolt
take evocation want to summon an army of
Undead choose necromancy in this section
we'll go through each subclass show you
what you get from each and show you what
spells fall under that category all
wizards gain subclass features at level
2 level 6 and finally again at level 10.
these subclass features are what set
Wizards apart from one another on top of
that wizards of a chosen school can
learn spells from Scrolls of that same
school for half the cost 25 gold instead
of 50 gold
note that they can still learn spells
from other schools it's just cheaper
from their chosen School moving into the
subclasses themselves first is
abduration
a level 2 AB duration Wizards gain
Arcane Ward Arcane Ward prevents damage
to the wizard equal to the number of
Arcane Ward strategies you have this
goes down by one whenever you take
damage and also increases by the level
of any AB duration spell you cast if you
cast more AB duration spells you will be
protected more
you can see on the screen AB duration
spells that Wizards can learn without
multi-classing
at level 6 AB duration Wizards can
sacrifice their Arcane Ward to reduce
the damage that nearby Ally takes this
allows them to protect damage to
themselves or their party members
at level 10 AB duration Wizards gain
improved app duration this makes it so
whenever they short rest they gain
Arcane War charges equal to their wizard
level
this makes short rest particularly good
for ab duration Wizards because remember
they only lose one charge when they take
damage
next up is evocation a level 2 evocation
Wizards learn sculpt spells which allows
them to cast evocation spells without
fear of damaging allies how many times
have you had multiple enemies group up
around your tank only to avoid casting
Fireball because they would be hit well
with this subclass you no longer have to
worry about this
you can see on the screen the list of
evocation spells that Wizards can learn
without multi-classing
oh
foreign
6 cantrips will now always deal at least
half the damage if an enemy saves
against them just remember this is only
with cantrips that Target abilities not
ones like Firebolt or Ray of frost that
Target armor
at level 10 evocation Wizards can add
their intelligence modifier to the
damage of their evocation spells note
that you'll only add this once with most
evocation spells not to each dice rolled
however if the spell has multiple
projectiles like magic Missile the extra
damage will apply to each one
next up is necromancy a level 2
necromancy Wizards gain Health back
equal to two times the level of the
spell slot used if they kill an enemy
and three times if it was a necromancy
spell they used
killing Undead and constructs does not
trigger this effect however
you can see on the screen necromancy
spells that Wizards can learn without
multi-classing
[Music]
at level 6 necromancy Wizards summon an
additional Undead when using the anime
dead spell and these summons have
increased hit points equal to the
Wizard's level
summons also gain additional damage
equal to the proficiency bonus of the
wizard if you like somebody Undead then
you will minimally want to take six
levels of necromancy wizard
at level 10 necromancy Wizards gain
resistance to necrotic damage cutting it
in half and they also cannot have their
Max ehp reduced
next is conjuration
at level 2 conjuration Wizards can cast
create water once per short rest without
consuming a spell slot
at level 6 conjuration Wizards can
teleport to an unoccupied space or
change positions with an ally within 9
meters this feature can only be used
once per long rest unless the wizard
casts another Conjuration Spell level
one or higher then they can use it again
you can see on the screen conjuration
spells that Wizards can learn without
multi-classing
[Music]
at level 10 conjuration Wizards
concentrating on a Conjuration Spell
cannot have their concentration broken
from taking damage
next is enchantment at level 2
enchantment Wizards can use hypnotic
gaze once per long rest which
incapacitates an enemy for two turns
preventing them from taking any action
bonus action or reaction as long as you
maintain your gaze
you can reapply this to them at the cost
of an action but any damage to the
Target will free them so it's best used
to remove one enemy completely from a
fight until you're ready to deal with it
at level 6 enchantment Wizards can use
the reaction to charm and enemy
attacking them once per round into
attacking another character this is
great for preventing damage to your
Wizard and does not require a short or
long rest to reuse
at level 10 enchantment Wizards can
Target two characters with enchantment
spells that normally Target one
you can see enchantment spells that
Wizards can learn without multi-classing
up on the screen now
next is divination at level 2 divination
Wizards gain 2 port and dice after every
long rest the number of these dice are
random and they can be used as a
reaction to replace the role of a nearby
friendly attack role or saving throw or
enemy attack roller saving throw apply
High numbers to friendlies and low
numbers to enemies
at level 6 divination Wizards gain a
third port and die every long rest and
can regain a spent port and die by
fulfilling a prophecy after each short
rest you can see what this prophecy is
by mousing over it next to your
character portrait on the left hand side
of the screen
at level 10 divination Wizards can gain
Superior dark vision and see
invisibility as actions that don't
require a spell slot until they long
rest divination spells that Wizards can
learn without multi-classing are up on
the screen now
you can see that there are a few
divination spells in bg3 which is why
their subclass features do not revolve
around these spells
next up is illusion at level 2 illusion
Wizards can cast minor illusion as a
bonus action instead of an action
additionally they can remain hidden
while casting it and can cast it even if
silence which would normally prevent
spell casting illusion spells that
Wizards can cast are up on the screen
now and these are ones they can learn
without multi-classing
at level 6 illusion Wizards can cast see
invisibility as an action without
consuming a spell slot once per long
rest
and at level 10 illusion Wizards can
make an illusory copy of themselves as a
reaction once per short rest when they
are attacked in combat causing the
attack to miss entirely
and lastly we come to transmutation at
level 2 transmutation Wizards have the
chance to create two alchemical
solutions when crafting if they pass the
medicine skill check with 15 difficulty
class
at level 6 transmutation Wizards can
craft a transmutation stone that
provides various benefits depending on
what you want once per long rest or
until you cast another transmutation
spell note that you can only have one
transmutation Stone created at a time
though you can give it to any character
you wish
you can see on the screen transmutation
spells that Wizards can learn without
multi-classing
[Music]
at level 10 transmutation Wizards can
change into a Blue Jay as an action and
flies a blue jay wood in order to reach
places you might not normally be able to
and now we come to multi-classing in
this section of our Boulder's Gate 3
wizard class guide we'll be taking a
look at multi-classing a wizard in bg3
and what other classes you might
multi-class with
keep in mind this is not a complete list
but rather helpful suggestions that make
good parents
Wizards typically multi-class with only
a few classes like Eldritch Knight
Arcane trickster or cleric however many
other classes dip one level into wizard
in order to be able to learn spells from
Scrolls these would still require
intelligence to cast but there are few
items in the game that boost
intelligence making this a non-issue
primary Wizards might multi-class after
level 2 because this is where they gain
their first subclass feature some of
them are pretty potent like sculpt
spells or improved minor illusion Rogues
gain a bonus feat at level 10 and
Eldritch Knight's gain their last
subclass feature at level 10 making it a
good spot if you want level 3 spell
slots and all subclass features of
Eldritch Knight or Arcane Trickster
the next most likely place to
multi-class would be after level 10
where each wizard gains their final
subclass feature dipping two levels in a
fighter can give a wizard action surge
so they can fling more spells in one
turn once per short rest or a level or
two of cleric can provide them with some
valuable proficiencies like heavy armor
and martial weapons from the war or
Tempest domains
that wraps up our bg3 wizard guide I
hope you guys found it useful I put all
the spells in here so you guys can get
an idea of like the Spells you might
focus on if you're you know picking a
wizard subclass not all wizard subclass
focuses on the Spells of that school but
a lot of them do and it really
influences the decision that you're
going to make as always if you have
other tips for other wizard players make
sure you leave them in the comments and
if you have questions leave them there
as well and I will try and answer them
as soon as I can
[Music]